Guide to the John V. Murra Papers ALBA.078
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John V. Murra Papers
1937-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Murra, John V.
Lechtman, Heather
Brandeis University
ALBA.078
0.25 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box
John V. Murra (1916-2006) was a Ukrainian-American professor of anthropology and researcher of the Inca Empire. Born in Ukraine, Murra emigrated to the United States in 1934 and completed an undergraduate degree in sociology at the University of Chicago (1936). From 1937 to 1939 he fought in the Spanish Civil War as a member of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. When Murra returned to the United States, he completed a master's degree (1942), and a Ph.D. (1956), both in anthropology at University of Chicago. The John V. Murra Papers (1937-1989) contain Murra's military identification card used while serving with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain (1937-1939), as well as scholarly articles written by Murra dating from the 1960s to the 1980s. The collection also contains a 1944 letter from the War Manpower Commission to Murra's employer requesting him for a position; a 1989 conference announcement; and a curriculum vitae from 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Brandeis University in January 2001. An accretion to the collection was donated by the Executrix of Murra's Estate, Heather Lechtman, in 2011. The accession numbers associated with these are: 1989.081 and 2011.048.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in alphabetical order.
Biographical Note
John V. Murra (1916-2006) was a Ukrainian-American professor of anthropology. Born in Ukraine, Murra emigrated to the United States in 1934 and completed an undergraduate degree in sociology at the University of Chicago in 1936. From 1937 to 1939, he fought in the Spanish Civil War as a member of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. When Murra returned to the United States, he went on to finish a master's degree in 1942, and a Ph.D. in 1956, both in anthropology, at the University of Chicago. His work primarily focused on the development of the Inca Empire.
Custodial History
The John V. Murra Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives and deposited at Brandeis University in 1989. The collection was transferred to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives in January 2001 as part of the relocation of the ALBA collections from Brandeis to New York University.
Related Materials
John V. Murra served as research assistant in the 1940s for Professor John Dollard's study Fear and Courage under Battle Conditions, which collected responses from U.S. volunteers about their reactions in battle. See the records for the John Dollard Research Files for Fear and Courage under Battle Conditions (ALBA 122).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains material related to John V. Murra, including an identification card used while serving with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (1937-1939) in Spain during the Spanish Civil War, and material from later in Murra's career as an anthropologist. Copies of articles related to the Incan Empire date from the 1960s to late 1980s. The collection also contains a 1944 letter from the War Manpower Commission encouraging Murra's employer release him and allow him to take a wartime position, a 1989 conference announcement, and a curriculum vitae from 1989.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Veterans.; Articles.; Lechtman, Heather; Murra, John V.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Brandeis University
- Articles -- Cloth and Its Functions in the Inca State, August 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Articles -- New Data on Retainer and Servile Populations in Tawantinsuyu, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles -- Book Review Written by Murra, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Articles -- El "Control Vertical" de un Maximo de Pisos Ecologicos en la Economia de los Sociedades Andinas, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Articles -- The "Vertical Control" of a Maximum of Ecological Tiers in the Economies of Andean Societies (Translated from Spanish), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Articles -- Los Limites y las Limitaciones del "Archipielago Vertical", en los Andes, circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Articles -- The Mit'a Oblications of Ethnic Groups to the Inka State, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Articles -- The Cultural Future of the Andean Majority, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Articles -- El Archipiélago Vertical: Once Años Después, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Articles -- An Interview with John V. Murra; Introduction by John Howland Rowe, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Articles -- Andean Societies, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Articles -- Andean Societies Before 1532, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Documents -- Letter from War Manpower Commission to Murra's Employer, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Documents -- Curriculum Vitae, July 1, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Documents -- Announcement of Conference in Honor of John V. Murra, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Documents -- Carnet Militar (Identity Card) with Photograph for the Spanish Republic International Brigade, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)